Guide to the Edwin Munsell Bliss Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edwin Munsell Bliss papers
1847-1912
1873-1883
MS 919
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Correspondence, writings and travel journals kept during Edwin Munsell Bliss's travels in the Near East while an agent for the American Bible Society in the Levant (1872-1888). His writings are devoted to his travels, and letters from family and friends also describe their experiences as missionaries living and traveling in the Near East. Also included is the will of Bliss's first wife, Marie Louise Henderson Bliss.
Bliss, Edwin Munsell, 1848-1919
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Edwin M. Bliss Papers deal for the most part with experiences of Americans living and traveling in the Middle East in the mid and late 1800s. Approximately one third of the collection is made up of essays written by Bliss (included are manuscript and typed drafts and galley proofs; many of the essays were probably published) describing his travels in the Near East, as well as Near Eastern and Biblical history. More detailed accounts of his travels can be found in his journals and letters written during a trip from Constantinople to Mesopotamia, Georgia, and Persia in 1879 and an undated trip from Alexandria to Khanakhi (Al-Khanakah) in Egypt. The papers contain correspondence of Bliss with family members and fellow missionaries, and some correspondence of his parents, Isaac and Eunice (Day) Bliss. Included are a journal in the form of a letter from Eunice Bliss describing her voyage to Turkey in 1847, and letters from her husband describing his travels around Turkey in the summer of 1850. Most of the Edwin Bliss correspondence is contained in two letterbooks covering the period 1873-1883; many of these letters offer lengthy discussions of political and social conditions in Constantinople and of his missionary work in the Ottoman Empire. Finally, also in the collection are Edwin Bliss's passports and travel documents and a draft of the will of Marie Louise (Henderson) Bliss.
Biographical / Historical
Edwin Munsell Bliss was born in Erzrum, Turkey, on September 12, 1848. He was the son of a minister sent to Constantinople by the American Bible Society for the Levant. He received an A.B. from Amherst College in 1871 and later studied at Yale Divinity School. He spent his life performing various jobs in the United States for the government and abroad with missionary organizations. He also worked for various newspapers, including a job at The Independent between 1891 and 1901. He was editor of the Encyclopedia of Missions. He was married to Marie Louise Henderson and after her death, to E. Theodora Crosby. He died on August 6, 1919.
Missionaries' spouses; Missionaries -- Middle East; Egypt -- Description and travel; Middle East -- Description and travel; Diaries; Clergy; Missionaries; Bliss, Edwin Munsell, 1848-1919; Bliss, Eunice Day; Bliss, Isaac Groot, 1822-1889; Bliss, Marie Louise Henderson, d. 1897
- Writings, 1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 17)
- Correspondence
  - Eunice (Day) Bliss, [1847?] July 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Isaac Groot Bliss, 1850 May 31-July 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Edwin M. Bliss
    - Letterbook, 1873-1883 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - ALS to his family, 1878 May 1-July 10, 1879 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 21 - 22)
    - ALS to unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Letterbook, 1878 May 9-June 26 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Travel journals
  - Journal of a trip from Constantinople to Persia, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 25 - 26)
  - Journal of Egyptian trip, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Travel documents, 1878-1879, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Marie Louise (Henderson) Bliss: draft of her will, [pre-1897 December 12] (Box 1, Folder 29)